University Senate; Records ua200
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
University Senate Records2001 November 18 - 2017 May 17
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York at Albany. University Senate
ua200
31 162 Captures
The University Senate is a legislative arm of the faculty comprised of 81 faculty, professional, and student senators. Records include legislation, meeting records, and Council Records.
Historical Note
The earliest predecessor of the University at Albany Senate (commonly referred to as the University Senate) was the Faculty Council, whose minutes date from 1915 through 1937. The Faculty Council, whose members consisted of the President, Deans, and faculty representatives, functioned as an advisory body on campus policy and academic affairs.[1] No records of the Faculty Council exist after May 1937.
In June 1944, at the urging of the New York State College for Teachers' chapter of the American Association of University Professors,[2] a Faculty-Administration Council was formed to facilitate cooperation between faculty and administration on any policy that "touches faculty-administration relationships and the general welfare of the college."[3] Its membership consisted of the President of the College, the Dean, other members of the administrative staff, and twelve elected faculty members. Six new faculty members, two from each academic rank, were elected in May of each year to serve two-year terms. Faculty membership in the Council would rise to eighteen by 1962, still equally divided by rank.[4] The faculty members of the Faculty-Administration Council held separate meetings as a Faculty Council "to consider common problems and policies, assign committee responsibilities in certain areas, and formulate recommendations to be submitted to the Faculty-Administration Council."[5] The last mention of a Faculty-Administration Council meeting appears in 1955.[6]
The Faculty Council's mission was to represent "the faculty as a whole.... act as a liaison and advisory body to the Administration... representing faculty opinion on matters of College policy and in the broader aspects of College planning" and "develop and sustain the best possible conditions of faculty life, work, and morale."[7] After 1955, liaison between the Faculty Council and the administration was achieved through a bi-monthly conference of the chairman of the Faculty Council and the President, at which meeting the President would raise questions he wanted the Faculty Council to discuss. On occasion, the President met with the full Council.[8] The Faculty Council continued to function until it was replaced by the Faculty Senate in 1966.
As the Faculty Council was transformed into a strictly faculty body, other councils were created to deal with increasingly complex problems of college governance. The first of these bodies was the Academic Council (1953-63), briefly called the College Advisory Council (1952-53), also referred to in the 1962 Faculty Handbook as the Administrative (Academic) Council.[9] It consisted of departmental chairmen and administrative representatives. Its responsibilities included acting on recommendations for undergraduate and graduate course changes and taking "broad curriculum changes to the faculty for a vote."[10] As graduate education assumed a more important role in the College, a Graduate Academic Council was created in 1963 consisting of the Director of Graduate Studies and eight members of the graduate faculty (four appointed by the President, and four elected by the graduate faculty). The Graduate Academic Council's responsibilities were to appoint "study committees on curriculum, admissions, and educational policy" as well as ad hoc committees as the need arose.[11] Shortly after the Graduate Academic Council was formed, President Collins dissolved the Academic Council and created an Undergraduate Academic Council whose membership and functions paralleled those of the Graduate Academic Council.[12] A Student Personnel Council was created, first mentioned in 1962, consisting of personnel staff and faculty appointed by the President. Its mission was to deal with questions involving student activities, counseling, loans and scholarships.[13] The proliferation of councils of the university, coupled with the rapid expansion of the school as it adapted to its new mission as a University Center, made reorganization of this structure imperative by the mid-sixties.[14]
In the spring of 1966, the University Faculty created the Faculty Senate out of the formerly independent councils of the University including the Faculty Council, the Undergraduate Academic Council, the Graduate Academic Council, and the Student Personnel Council. The mission of the new Faculty Senate included the delegated authority of the University Faculty, granted by the SUNY Board of Trustees, to "participate in the development of educational programs... and be responsible for the conduct of the college's instruction, research, and service programs."[15] In addition to these broad delegated powers, the Faculty Senate was also granted the power to form the agenda for meetings, create councils and committees, administer faculty financial affairs, call for referenda, consult on major University reorganizations and appointments, and issue annual reports to the faculty.[16]
This reorganization reflected the broader conception of the faculty adopted in the SUNYA Faculty by-laws of March 1966,[17] which as applied to the Faculty Senate included as ex-officio members representatives of the SUNY Central Administration, the major administrative officers of SUNYA, local campus representatives of the SUNY Faculty Senate, as well as at large, college, and school representatives of the voting faculty, and voting faculty appointed by the President.[18]
The Faculty Senate changed its name to the University Senate in October 1969 when student representation was added to the body. Beginning in the fall of 1970, student representation consisted of 33 Senators, one third elected from the graduate body and two thirds from the undergraduate body.[19] In the 1980s, student representation decreased. By 1990, student representation consisted of 15 Senators, 1 elected from the graduate body and 14 from the undergraduate body.[20] With minor variations in the representation of the different groups, the make-up of the Senate has remained the same for a number of years. The University Senate remains the principal policy-making body of the University.
Notes 1. Faculty Council, Minutes, 1915. There was no specific statement of function for the Faculty Council. The purpose of the Faculty Council was established by reading the minutes. 200/01/012. "Suggested Plan for a Faculty-Administration Council for the New York State College for Teachers," May 1, 1944.3. "Faculty-Administration Council General Rules to Govern Elections and Operations," circa 1944. 200/01/014. Faculty Handbook, 1962, pp. 16-17.5. Faculty Handbook, 1952, p. 11.6. Faculty Council, Annual Report, 1954-55, p. 1.7. Faculty Handbook, 1962, pp. 16-17.8. Faculty Council, Annual Report, 1955-56, p. 2.9. Academic Council, Agendas and Minutes, 1952-53, 200/02/01; Faculty Handbook, 1962, p. 16.10. Faculty Handbook, 1962, p. 16.11. Faculty Handbook, 1962, p. 20.12. Academic Council, Minutes, October 21, 1963. 200/02/0113. Faculty Handbook, 1962, p. 20. For the records of the Student Personnel Council, see the Office of the President, Records, President Evan Collins, Subject Files. 00014. "Report of the Ad Hoc Committee of the Faculty Council on the Nature of the University," October 1965, pp. 6-8, in particular voiced the Faculty's frustration at not being involved in major decisions affecting the University. Subsequent attempts to ratify new Faculty By-Laws which codified the proliferation of University councils were rejected by the Faculty Council in December 1965. Faculty Council Bulletin, December 15, 1965.15. State University of New York, Policies of the Board of Trustees, 1962, X, sect. 4, p. 13.16. Faculty Handbook, 1966-67, "Faculty By-Laws," Article I, sect. 3.1, Article II, sect. 1.1-1.7, pp. 7.1-7.3.17. Faculty Handbook, 1966-67, Article I, sect. 1, p. 7.1.18. Ibid., Article II, sect. 2.1, p. 7.3.19. Faculty Handbook, 1970-71, Article II, sect. 2.6-2.7, p. 13.20. Faculty Handbook, 1990-92, Article II, sect. 2.6-2.7, p. 11.
Scope and Contents
The records of the University Senate include agendas and minutes, correspondence, memoranda, reports, bills, resolutions, and legislation relating to the University Senate (November 1969 to present), and its predecessor organizations, the Faculty Senate (May 1966-October 1969) the Faculty Council (1915-37, 1944-66), the Faculty- Administration Council (1945-54/55), the Academic Council (1952-63), the Undergraduate Academic Council (1963-66), and the Graduate Academic Council (1964-66). Some minutes of the Faculty-Administration Council are bound with the minutes of the Faculty Council (1944-47). No records exist for the years 1938 through 1943.
The records of the University Senate and its predecessor bodies contain discussions of faculty academic and social life, changes in academic programs, regulations of student academic and social life, major university reorganization plans, and the composition of the University Senate and its councils. Specific topics discussed include the addition of administrators and students to the University Senate in the late 1960s, the Senate's official statement on the Vietnam War (1970), the University's policy on protests and demonstrations (1967), the implementation of s/u grading in 1969, the elimination of the general degree requirements for a liberal arts education (the CURE proposal) in 1970 and the reimplementation of degree requirements in the 1980s, the development of multidisciplinary majors such as Judaic Studies and Puerto Rican Studies in 1974 and Chinese Studies and Asian Studies in 1979, and the University's smoking policy. Bound with the Faculty Council minutes (1915-37) are the minutes of general Faculty Meetings.
The records of the University Senate are divided into subgroups, and these subgroups represent either the records of predecessor organizations, the general records of the University Senate or the records of the individual councils of the Senate. The records of councils' committees are found following that council's general records.
A keyword index is included to facilitate subject access to the general body of this finding aid. Also included in this finding aid is a list of legislation from 1966 to 1980, arranged by academic year and bill number. Following that appendix is a subject index to legislation from 1980 to 1988, prepared by Madelyn Cicero, secretary to the University Senate. The University Archives has not received any Senate legislation from the period 1980 through 1988. These two appendixes are not covered by the keyword index.
Arrangement of the Collection
The records were reorganized in 2016 to be consistant with the Senate's current recordkeeping practices. Records are divided into series based on recors type and use.
Acquisition Information
These records were transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives, University Libraries, University at Albany, by the University Senate. Paper records aere transferred prior to 2014, and likely prior to 2001. Since 2016, records are created, managed, and maintained only in digital form. Most records since the early 2000s were born-digital and managed by Elisa Lopez, secretary in the President's Office. After 2016 these records are automatically transferred to the arhices periodically as they are created.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Athletics and Sports; Higher education--New York (State); Wages -- New York (State); Web Archives; State University of New York at Albany
- Website of the University Senate, 2001 November 18 - 2017 May 17; 1; 162 captures
  URL
  http://www.albany.edu/senate/
  Access Requirements
  The item contains web archives preserved as WARC files. They must be access though web archival replay tools such as the "Wayback Machine." The links here direct you to files hosted by the Internet Archive, but you may also request WARC files.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Web crawling is managed through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service.
  This item is not a seed within an Archive-it collection, but capures of this page are found within:
  collection: University at Albany, SUNY Website
  created_date: 2012-09-17T13:15:00Z
  created_by: bkeough
  state: ACTIVE
  last_updated_date: 2016-09-26T23:38:05Z
  last_updated_by: system
  Web Collection
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2001 November 18
    This crawl was performed by the Internet Archive, not the UAlbany web archiving program, so the provenance is unknown.
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2001 November 22
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2002 June 12
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2002 December 18
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2003 April 15
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2003 August 12
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2003 October 15
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2004 February 4
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2004 April 7
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2004 August 5
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2004 September 6
  - University at Albany -- University Senate, 2004 October 10
  - Senate Homepage, 2005 February 7
  - Senate Homepage, 2005 September 9
  - Senate Homepage, 2005 September 23
  - Senate Homepage, 2005 October 17
  - Senate Homepage, 2005 October 31
  - Senate Homepage, 2005 December 12
  - UNIVERSITY SENATE HOMEPAGE, 2006 February 20
  - UNIVERSITY SENATE HOMEPAGE, 2006 May 3
  - UNIVERSITY SENATE HOMEPAGE, 2006 June 18
  - UNIVERSITY SENATE HOMEPAGE, 2006 August 29
  - UNIVERSITY SENATE HOMEPAGE, 2006 September 8
  - UNIVERSITY SENATE HOMEPAGE, 2006 October 5
  - UNIVERSITY SENATE HOMEPAGE, 2006 December 6
  - Senate Home, 2007 March 4
  - Senate Home, 2007 June 8
  - Senate Home, 2007 October 31
  - Senate Home, 2007 November 23
  - Senate Home, 2008 January 22
  - Senate Home, 2008 March 24
  - Senate Home, 2008 May 9
  - Senate Home, 2008 May 23
  - Senate Home, 2008 September 14
  - Senate Home, 2009 January 25
  - Senate Home, 2009 April 8
  - Senate Home, 2009 November 24
  - Senate Home, 2010 February 19
  - Senate Home, 2010 April 21
  - Senate Home, 2010 May 27
  - Senate Home, 2010 June 23
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2011 October 10
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2011 December 4
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2012 May 14
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2012 July 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2012 July 2
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2012 September 30
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2012 December 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 January 2
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 February 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 February 17
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 March 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 March 15
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 April 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 May 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 May 8
    This item had no crawl rules.
    The CDX index for this capture did not contain crawl information.
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 May 8
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Researchers interested in data analysis with web archives may request a WARC file. WARC files are very large and difficult to work with. Your request may take time to process, and we may be unable to deliver your request remotely. Please consult an archivist if you are interested in advanced research with web archives.
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 May 8
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 May 8
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 May 29
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 May 29
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 June 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 June 26
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 June 26
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 July 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 July 3
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 July 3
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 July 31
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 July 31
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 August 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 August 14
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 August 14
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 September 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 September 4
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 September 4
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 September 11
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 September 11
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 September 25
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 September 25
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 October 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 October 23
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 October 23
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 October 30
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 October 30
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 November 13
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 November 13
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 December 11
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 December 11
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 December 18
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 December 18
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 December 25
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2013 December 25
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 January 1
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 January 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 January 22
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 January 22
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 January 29
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 January 29
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 February 5
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 February 5
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 February 12
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 February 12
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 February 26
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 February 26
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 March 5
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 March 5
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 March 12
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 March 12
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 March 19
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 March 19
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 March 26
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 March 26
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 April 2
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 April 2
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 April 9
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 April 9
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 April 16
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 April 16
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 April 23
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 April 23
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 April 30
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 April 30
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 May 7
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 May 7
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 May 21
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 May 21
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 May 28
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 May 28
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 June 4
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 June 4
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 June 11
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 June 11
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 July 2
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 July 2
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 July 23
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 July 23
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 July 30
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 July 30
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 August 13
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 August 13
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 September 3
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 September 3
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 September 17
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 September 17
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 September 24
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 September 24
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 1
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 1
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 8
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 8
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 15
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 15
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 22
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 22
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 24
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 29
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 October 29
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 November 5
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 November 5
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 November 19
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 November 19
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 November 26
  - WARC file for University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 November 26
  - University Senate - University at Albany-SUNY, 2014 December 10